Guide to the Richard Pollay Acme Advertising Collection, 1850s-2006 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richard Pollay Acme Advertising collection 1850s-2006 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Pollay, Richard.
75 linear feet Extent: 3000 Items
The Acme Advertising Collection is one of the collections created by Professor Richard Pollay in the History of Advertising Archives (Faculty of Commerce, Sauder School of Business, University of British Columbia). The collection was motivated by the observation that Acme named enterprises are characteristically small ventures that represent the grass roots of local and regional economies. At the same time, the ubiquity of the Acme brand name has made its way into popular culture, where it has become an icon for independent business in general, featured in print cartoons from artists such as Gary Larson (The Far Side) and G.B. Trudeau (Doonesbury), and in the Warner Bros. animated Road Runner features. Items in the Acme Collection come from a variety of sources. Many items were donated to Dr. Pollay, but the majority were acquired by Dr. Pollay himself over several decades. In earlier years items were found in shops, flea markets, and antique stores across North America. However, in recent years most items were acquired through the internet auction site, eBay (www.eBay.com). The Acme Advertising Collection dates from the 1850s through 2006 and consists of approximately 3000 items from over 900 distinct companies and producers, primarily of U.S. or Canadian origin, all bearing the brand name Acme. The collection contains a diverse array of items, both three-dimensional and printed materials, including: promotional items and memorabilia; trade cards; business cards; magazine tear sheets; catalogs; newspaper clippings; signs; displays; writing instruments; rulers; clothing; toys and games; school and office stationery supplies; photographs and slides. A number of corporations are represented in the collection, including: Acme Bail Bonds; Acme Boots; Acme Brick Company; Acme Harvester; Acme Markets; Acme Motor Truck Company; Acme White Lead and Color Works; Duane H. Nash, Inc.; Lautz Bros. and Company; and Warner Bros.
RL.01032
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Richard Pollay Acme Advertising Collection were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006.
Collection Overview
The Acme Advertising Collection dates from the 1850s through 2006 and consists of approximately 3000 items from over 900 distinct companies and producers, primarily of U.S. or Canadian origin, all bearing the brand name Acme. The collection contains a diverse array of items, both three-dimensional and printed materials, including: promotional items and memorabilia; trade cards; business cards; magazine tear sheets; catalogs; newspaper clippings; signs; displays; writing instruments; rulers; clothing; toys and games; school and office stationery supplies; photographs and slides. A number of corporations are represented in the collection, including: Acme Bail Bonds; Acme Boots; Acme Brick Company; Acme Harvester; Acme Markets; Acme Motor Truck Company; Acme White Lead and Color Works; Duane H. Nash, Inc.; Lautz Bros. and Company; and Warner Brothers.
A significant part of the collection is organized and grouped to represent rooms in a house. For example, kitchen items have been collected together. Office, wardrobe, and bathroom items are similarly gathered. Most items are represented in the Detailed Description by thumbnail images. In all, the collection consists of 28 Series: Kitchen Collectibles; Wardrobe and Bedroom Collectibles; Toys, Games, Sports and Recreation; Office and School Supplies; Domestic Hardware; Grocery and Store Collectibles; ACME Beer; Warner Brothers; Clothing Collectibles; Industrial Hardware; Bottles and Jars; Catalogs; Stationery and Certificates; Books and Monographs; Specialty Advertisements; Posters, Magazine, and Newspaper Advertisements; Sales Oddities; Photographs; eBay Files; Acme Bail Bonds; Acme Truck; Audiovisual Materials; Match Covers; Telephone Directories; Business Cards; Trade Cards; Slides; and Miscellaneous Items.
The collection arrived already organized into 28 series. Every item had been assigned an accession number, a unique 8-digit identifier, in the format 100-xx-xxx: the middle digits refer to the Series number, and the last three digits represent a running accession sequence within the Series. Items have been arranged by Series and numerically therein; however, there are a few exceptions where items have been transferred to another series after having been previously assigned an accession number. The collection also arrived with a descriptive database that was created and maintained by Professor Pollay's staff. The item descriptions in this finding aid represent a distillation of that database into a form more consistent with EAD-compliant finding aids. The collection has been minimally processed, with the original order maintained as much as possible. In addition, some items have been deaccessioned or retained by the donor, and only a digital image of the item exists in the collection. Those have been noted in the inventory.
Series 1: Kitchen Collectibles consists of Acme products for kitchen use: juice extractors; sifters; cast iron pans; and other utensils.
Series 2: Wardrobe and Bedroom Collectibles consists of Acme products for use in the bedroom or used as part of a wardrobe, including shoe pads, zippers, scissors, etc.
Series 3: Toys, Games, Sports and Recreation includes Acme toys and games, and other items used in sports and recreation, including model cars, toy trains, whistles, and playing cards.
Series 4: Office and School Supplies includes Acme products used as office and school supplies: erasers, staplers, rulers, pencils, etc.
Series 5: Domestic Hardware includes objects related to hardware used in homes, including wall thermometers; padlocks; iron hinges; and binoculars.
Series 6: Grocery and Store Collectibles includes grocery items such as evaporated milk, potato bags, bread bags, store signs, product display signs, and postcards.
Series 7: ACME Beer includes bottles, tins, catalogs, souvenir programs, flat advertisements and advertising objects relating to the Acme brand of beer.
Series 8: Warner Brothers consists of advertising objects and novelty items from Warner Bros. that feature the Acme label: Wile E Coyote lapel pin; Acme Optical glass case; along with clothing items like neckties, waist pouches, sweatshirts, and hats.
Series 9: Clothing Collectibles consists of clothing items featuring the Acme label and includes aprons, caps and T-shirts.
Series 10: Industrial Hardware includes industrial type objects like printing plates, radio control switches, etc.
Series 11: Bottles and Jars consists of bottles, glassware and jars featuring the Acme name or logo Also included are two colored glass slides, a baby's bottle and items in glass picture frames.
Series 12: catalogs includes various-sized catalogs, brochures, ledgers, and flyers. They are: Acme Trading Co., Acme Boot Co., and Acme Brick. Each item is individually described.
Series 13: Stationery and Certificates consists of assorted business stationery and certificates, including examples of late 19th century and early 20th century lithography on bond certificates and company letter heads. The companies Duane H. Nash Inc., Acme Harvester Co., and Acme Shear Co. provide examples of typical workmanship.
Series 14: Books and Monographs includes books, picture books, monographs and magazines that feature the Acme sign or logo or make mention of Acme.
Series 15: Specialty Advertisements consists primarily of promotional items such as blotters; small calendars; stickers; and slide charts that feature an Acme logo or trademark.
Series 16: Posters, Magazine, and Newspaper Advertisements consists of print advertisements; mounted clippings; and photocopies of stationery and other paper items. Several companies are featured, including: Acme Boot Co., Acme Card System Co., Acme Harvester Co., Acme White Lead and Color Paint Works, Acme Wagon Co., Acme Washing Machine Co., and Acme Visible Card System. Each item is individually described. Each item carries an accession number.
Series 17: Sales Oddities consists of various advertising objects that feature an Acme logo or trademark, including both printed and three-dimensional objects such as tokens, pocket items, patches and decals.
Series 18: Photographs consists of photographs, negatives, and reprints of various shops, billboard, signs, and buildings featuring the Acme sign or logo. There are several pictures from Acme News Pictures, Inc. and Acme Telephoto, both press agencies.
Series 19: eBay Files consists of printouts from eBay.com relating to Acme-branded items. Printouts are housed in binders which are arranged roughly by year.
Series 20: Acme Bail Bonds consists of mostly printed materials related to the Acme Bail Bonds Company.
Series 21: Acme Truck consists of print advertisements for the Acme Truck, predominantly dating 1918-1922.
Series 22: Audiovisual Materials consists of sound and video recordings on various formats: cassette and video tapes; CD-ROM; vinyl records; and CDs. Each item features Acme as a trademark or logo or as part of the band name.
Series 23: Match Covers consists of assorted matchbook covers featuring the Acme label. Items are housed in a binder.
Series 24: Telephone Directories consists of the advertising Yellow pages. The provenance of these advertisements is largely unknown. The Series reflects the order in which they were collected.
Series 25: Business Cards consists of 138 business cards from various Acme companies. Items are housed in one binder.
Series 26: Trade Cards consists of various trading cards that were produced between the late 1880s and the 1930s. The bulk of items comes from the Lautz Bros Soap Co.
Series 27: Slides consists of 232 slides of various objects, locations and businesses featuring the name Acme. Slides are housed in one binder.
Series 28: Miscellaneous Items consists of miscellaneous items featuring the Acme label, name or trademark. Includes gas masks, farm implements, etc.
Subject Headings
Pollay, Richard W.; Acme Brick Company; Acme Markets, Inc.; Acme Newspictures (New York, N.Y.); Duane H. Nash, Inc.; Warner Bros; Advertising -- History -- Canada -- 20th century; Advertising -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Advertising -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising -- United States -- History -- 21st century; Advertising cards; Business cards; Pens -- Collectors and collecting; Signs and signboards; Toys -- Collectors and collecting; Advertising cards; Business cards; Clippings; Collectibles; Letterheads; Memorabilia; Photographs; Slides; Tear sheets; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Series 1: Kitchen Collectibles, 1876-1998 and undated
  - 100-01-001. Wal-Mart Stores, 1998 (Box 1)
    White plastic sifter with Acme Mini Sifter in red letters on one side; comes with original card which reads Mini-Gadget It really works! Verso of card lists features of sifter. Made in China.
  - 100-01-002. Acme International, Inc., 1998 (Box 1)
    Plastic red gum ball machine magnet still encased in original plastic packaging and card. #92001. Acme logo (black letter A with blue star in the center) found on both sides of card. Made in China.
  - 100-01-003. Acme International Inc., 1995 (Box 1)
    One plastic note clip magnet designed with short, sharpened yellow pencil with Acme 2 on it and a lined notepad with the words note clip. Embossed at the back: c 1995 Acme China. On back of magnet is a barcode label. Made in China.
  - 100-01-004. Acme International, Inc., 1998 (Box 1)
    Metal mini coarse grater in its original packaging and card. Front of card reads: Mini-gadget coarse grater, It really works! #96530. Back of card shows Acme logo and production information. In mint condition. Acme grater engraved on item. Made in China.
  - 100-01-005. Acme Juice Extractor, 1930s (Box 1)
    Metal juicer with text etched faintly around the spout: Acme Juice Extractor Turn into front this way (drawing of an arrow) Made in USA Pat. Pend. No company information on item. See 100-01-06 for the final patented product and for source of company information.
  - 100-01-006. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company, 1935 (Box 1)
    Metal juicer for oranges, grapefruits, lemons, limes and apples, meant to be inserted into fruit; comes in its original box of the Acme box colors: black and orange. Box has illustrated instructions on use and cleaning of item. Box doubles as a mailing box, complete with a note to the Postmaster that it can be opened for postal inspection if necessary. Except for slight tear on box lid, item and box are in good condition.
  - 100-01-007. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Acme Twin Curl Cutter, 1935 (Box 1)
    Thin metal utensil with curled, pointed tip and two rings on either side of base of cutter. Seems to be missing a T handle. Slightly discolored. Envelope has the black and orange colors of Acme packaging. Envelope is stained, torn at corner and creased. Front of envelope reads: The Acme Twin Cutter, tastefully served food tastes better. Price 50 cents. Reverse side carries directions on how to use and keep it clean and bright-- rinse thoroughly with hot water and place over a hot stove to dry.
  - 100-01-008. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Acme Twin Curl Cutter, 1935 (Box 1)
    Thin metal utensil with curled, pointed tip and two rings on either side of base of cutter. Seems to be missing a T handle. Item shows discoloration. Original envelope has green and brown colors (instead of orange and black Acme colors). Text on front includes: tastefully served food tastes better. Price 50 cents; stamp and star of approval by General Housekeeping Institute on front; reverse side has directions on use and cleaning. Torn and creased in several places.
  - 100-01-009. American Stores Company, undated (Box 1)
    One empty coffee can with painted label; Acme brand coffee on one side; picture of a coffee pot and cup of hot coffee with its steam spelling out Acme Coffee on other side. Comes with lid with Acme Brand Coffee embossed on it. Background shows coffee berries and a lower panel of white dots against a red background. Dents in couple places; may have been used for other purposes. Paint scratched off in several places. American Stores Company is the distributor.
  - 100-01-010. Woofer's Acme dog biscuit mix, 1990s (Box 1)
    One empty brown box complete with bone shaped tin cookie cutter. Text on box includes Dog Easy Directions to make 34 delicious dog bone treats; ingredient and nutritional information. Text on sides of box: Adored by dogs worldwide regardless of breed! Manufactured exclusively for Restoration Hardware by Woofer's. In mint condition.
  - 100-01-011. Whirley, undated (Box 1)
    One plastic blue and gray coffee mug with lid. Acme registered trademark, with the boot inside the letter c, is painted all over the mug. Base of the mug reads: Whirley, Warren, Penn., USA; Patent Pending; and the recycling symbol LDPE 4. Lots of scratches on lid.
  - 100-01-012. Acme Laundry, undated (Box 1)
    Sportsman set with two utensils: can and bottle opener and ice pick in a clear plastic container. Both have plastic handles with red tips; ice pick has a plastic cover for its tip. Text on handles reads: Acme Laundry Call PA 2-5250 Sales Builder Sample L-208-212. Patent Pend inscribed on reverse side of opener. Handles have drawings of a man fishing (ice pick) and a man cooking barbecue (opener).
  - 100-01-013. Unknown. Sifter, undated (Box 1)
    Metal flour sifter; sifter turner has wooden handle; wire strainer is intact but with couple of holes. Acme in capital letters is embossed on front of sifter. Item shows discoloration and rust. Seems worn out from use.
  - 100-01-014. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Mender set, undated (Box 1)
    Set of 5 circular menders for repairing leaks in assorted sizes and 1 reamer wrench attached to card. Text on front side of blue and orange card includes Rustless material, No cement, rivet or solder required, Can be used at once, No waiting. Text on reverse side carries description of menders, directions and illustrations. Card shows minor stains and some water damage. Reamer wrench in rusty condition.
  - 100-01-015. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Acme French Fry Cutter and Garnishers, 1930s (Box 1)
    Two metal latticed-shaped cutters and garnishers with red wooden handles; attached to cards. Front side of card reads: For: Fancy French Fries, Latticed Potatoes...Corrugated edges on Grapefruit...Sandwiches...Chopping Onions... and includes directions. Reverse side of card gives full directions and illustrations on how to use item. On one corner is a drawing of a woman in an apron holding the item with text: Makes any hostess a food artist. Items show discoloration; some stains and creases on cards.
  - 100-01-016. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Acme garnishing set, 1935 (Box 1)
    Box set consists of a garnisher, a ball cutter and a slicer and shredder; all made of metal and red wooden handles. Box in poor condition, tears on several places, one of the lids held by tape; other side of box missing its cover. Text on back of box includes instructions and illustrations on how to use the three utensils. One side reads: tastefully served food tastes better; other side reads: An invaluable aid in preparing attractive dishes quickly.
  - 100-01-017. Raymond Products and Industries (Canada) Ltd. Acme decorating set, undated (Box 1)
    Set of decorating tips in its original box: a red plastic gadget with 5 circular metal cutters, and a plastic-lined icing cone with 5 plastic tips and 4 metal tips. Red plastic gadget is a product of Popeil Bros, Chicago, Ill. Text on box includes: The Acme set now makes it easy to be an expert. One side gives general instructions on use; the other side has 3 recipes. Paper box is stained and torn in several places; flaps are all that are left of the lids.
  - 100-01-018. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Acme rotary mincer, 1935 (Box 1)
    One metal mincer with cutting wheels and red wooden handle. Bottom side of orange and black box has instructions on use of mincer to mince vegetables, cut noodles and tenderize steaks; cleaning directions on other side of box. On one side of the box, text reads: tastefully served food tastes better. Slight tear on side of box; mincer in excellent condition.
  - 100-01-019. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Chopper/Slicer, undated (Box 1)
    One stainless steel chopper and slicer at its centre; with green painted metal handle. On reverse side of chopper: Pat. Pend. Stainless Steel and the triangle logo of Acme MGM Company. Scratches on steel chopper; paint on handle quite worn out.
  - 100-01-020. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Grater, 1933 (Box 1)
    One metal grater which doubles as a cake-cooling rack. Comes in original envelope. Reverse side of envelope states the safety features of the grater, its economical features, directions on use, health promotion info and list of food items it can grate. Front side of envelope carries seal of approval from Good Housekeeping Institute. Price on envelope: 50 cents. Creases and couple of tears on envelope. Slight discoloration on grater.
  - 100-01-021. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Acme safety grater and vegetable juice extractor, 1937 (Box 2)
    One grater that doubles as a strainer, dicer and cake-cooling rack; inscribed on handle: ACME The only genuine safety grater pat'd and made in USA. On reverse side of envelope are illustrations and directions. Stains, signs of water damage and tears on envelope. On left hand corner of envelope is a drawing of the grater under the microscope: Cutting edges of special triangular wire used. Inferior imitations use ordinary round wire which has no cutting edge. Item in excellent condition.
  - 100-01-022. Acme Metal Goods Manufacturing Company. Acme spiral splicer, 1935 (Box 2)
    One metal splicer with screw-like tip on one end an a circular handle on the other end; Acme MGM Company triangle logo on reverse side of item. Blue and orange colors on the Acme box; front side displays blue star; reverse side provides directions on use. One side reads: tastefully served food tastes better. Other side has cleaning instructions. Discoloration on item. Some stains on box.
  - 100-01-023. Unknown. Acme bottle caps, undated (Box 2)
    Three metal bottle caps; Made in USA around the little knob; traces of paint.
  - 100-01-024. Acme Tea Company. Tea tin, undated (Box 2)
    One empty tin from Acme Tea Company; red and gold colors and designs. Scratches, rust stains on item. Lid is shut tight.
  - 100-01-025. Worth and Pontifex. Graniteware mug, undated (Box 1)
    One white, blue-rimmed graniteware mug with blue handle; on one side of mug is an illustration of a woman in a Victorian gown. Text reads: Acme (inflated) dress improver. Worth and Pontifex, Waterproofers, Grosvenor Gardens, Trenton. Paint is chipped in several places. Film of dirt on bottom inside the mug. Residue of glue from sticker outside of mug.
  - 100-01-026. Acme Humble Pie Company. Pie plate, undated (Box 2)
    One tin pie plate with trademark of Acme Humble Pie Company etched in the center of pie plate. Scratches on item. Evidence of use.
  - 100-01-027. Acme Coal Company. Coal spoon, undated (Box 2)
    One metal coal spoon with Acme Coal Company--Phone 6-1183 on handle. Etched on spoon: Level Full 1/4 cup. Spoon is tarnished.
  - 100-01-028. Acme cast iron pan, 1876 (Box 2)
    One small cast iron pan with Pat-Acme-Nov.76. Evidence of much use.
  - 100-01-029. Unknown (No company name). Acme Cookie Maker, 1930s (Box 2)
    Text reads: Each press makes a cookie. Select your design and out they come. Metal cookie maker with all attachments for cookies and icing. Evidence of some rust. Box is worn and has one significant tear. Circa 1920s? Good condition.
  - 100-01-030. Unknown (No company name). Acme Coring device, undated (Box 2)
    Text reads: Acme Coremaster. Stainless Steel. Made in USA. Item has small plastic (?) handle. Good condition.
  - 100-01-031. Acme Can Company. Acme 5 Minute Gearless Ice Cream Spike, undated (Box 2)
    Varnished wooden handle, image of ice-cream pail on one side. Lettering not clear. Metal spike protrudes other end. Comes to blunt point. Rust. Good condition. Company ID taken from advertisement: See 100-12-100.
  - 100-01-032. Applause Inc. Coffee mug, 1987 (Box 2)
    One ceramic mug with Bugs Bunny surrounded by barrels and boxes of Acme T. N. T, explosives, dynamite, fireworks and gunpowder; text reads: My life is one big accident waiting to happen. Bottom of mug has the Applause trademark, copyright with Walt Disney Company and Amblin Entertainment, Inc. Made in Korea.
  - 100-01-033. Acme Chevrolet Company Inc. Steak knives, undated (Box 2)
    Text reads: Thanks! Acme Chevrolet Co. Inc., Robinson, Ill., Stainless Steel Steak Knives. Original box contains 4 plastic handled stainless steel knives. Made in Japan.
  - 100-01-034. Acme tin lunch box, undated (Box 2)